If you’re anything like me,
you have lots of ambitious
plans for the future.
I’ve got a whole series of
new books I want to write,
thousands more
videos to script.
But guess what?
None of us may be able to do
any of the things we want to do
if we don't have our health.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
There are all kinds of claims about
the red wine compound resveratrol.
One is that it helps us live longer
and it benefits our metabolic health.
But what does the science say?
In our first story, we ask:
is the red wine molecule responsible
for the so-called “French paradox”?
Resveratrol became a
household word in 1991
when a scientist
from Bordeaux University
appeared on the popular TV show
"60 Minutes"
and attributed
the so-called French Paradox
to the French habit
of drinking red wine.
The term "French Paradox"
itself
was coined in the newsletter
of the International
Organization of Vine and Wine
to explain a curious finding.
If you chart death
from heart attack
versus the amount
of saturated fat
and cholesterol consumed
in different countries,
there appears to be
a straight line.
The more animal-based foods
populations eat,
the higher their death rates
appear to be.
However, two countries
didn't fall in line
with that straight line.
Finland seemed to be doing
worse than expected,
and France appeared to be doing
better than expected.
Hence, the paradox.
How could France
have saturated fat
and cholesterol intake
similar to Finland,
but five times fewer
fatal heart attacks?
Everyone had their pet theories
to explain the paradox.
Was it the wining?
Was it the dining?
Yes, animal foods
are associated
with coronary heart disease
mortality,
but plant foods
appear to be protective.
So, might the fact
that the French were eating
four times as many vegetables
help account
for their lower death rates?
It turns out, however,
that there may be
no paradox at all.
According to an investigation
by the World Health
Organization,
French physicians were
just under-reporting
heart disease deaths
on the death certificates.
So, if you correct for that,
France basically comes
right back in line
with the death
versus animal fat
and death
versus cholesterol lines,
with about four times
the fatal heart attack rates
as Japan and about four times
the animal fat consumption.
By the time of the correction,
however,
resveratrol research
had already taken root,
culminating in more than 17,000
scientific publications to date.
But only about 1 to 2 percent
of the published reports
were human clinical trials,
and after many millions
of dollars spent
and many years
of disappointing results,
the scientific tide
started to turn.
Reviews began to ask whether
resveratrol was a molecule
whose time had come and gone:
"Should we now consign
resveratrol
to our intellectual
garbage cans
and move on to better things?"
Of course,
it didn't help matters
when a leading
resveratrol researcher
was found guilty of 145 counts
of fabrication
and falsification of data,
throwing the whole field
into turmoil.
But in 2013, resveratrol
was primed to make a comeback
with the apparent confirmation
that it was a STAC,
a sirtuin-activating compound,
that is, a compound
that purportedly activates
a longevity enzyme.
This has been called
into question, though.
Commentaries with titles like
"Is resveratrol an imposter?"
"Promising therapeutic,
or hopeless illusion?"
and "The resveratrol fiasco"
were published,
suggesting that the seeming
sirtuin activity
was probably the result
of experimental artifacts.
"In summary," a recent review
concluded, "the jury is out."
The proof is in the pudding,
though.
Does resveratrol enhance
longevity or not?
Yeast is the big success story,
with resveratrol
extending the lifespan
of brewer's yeast
by up to 70 percent.
Resveratrol also helped
microscopic roundworms
live longer,
but it failed fruit flies,
mosquitoes, and water fleas.
Anything bigger than
a unicellular fungus
or a microscopic worm?
Yes, resveratrol can extend
the lives of honeybees
and, most excitingly,
two vertebrates,
short-lived fish:
Gunther's
and turquoise killifish.
Unfortunately, most studies
on mammals (mostly mice)
failed to show
a lifespan benefit.
Resveratrol is said
to extend the life
of so-called model organisms
by mimicking
calorie restriction,
but flies and mice show
robust life-extension responses
to dietary restriction,
yet don't seem responsive
to resveratrol.
That may just be true
of healthy animals, though.
Give resveratrol to mice
in extremis,
whether bombarded by radiation,
poisoned with endotoxins,
or having their intestines
punctured
to cause sepsis-induced
kidney failure,
and they do survive longer
with resveratrol
than they otherwise would
under those circumstances.
Resveratrol
can also help mediate
the life-shortening effects
of high-fat diets in mice.
The lifespans
of healthy mice and rats
fed normal diets are not
affected by resveratrol,
but the compound
partially prevented
the premature deaths of mice
fed high-fat diets.
The authors of a meta-analysis
of the effect of resveratrol
on longevity across species
concluded
that, based on the fact
that most mouse studies
failed to show a benefit,
it's "inappropriate
for resveratrol to be marketed
as a life-extending
health supplement."
True, no study has demonstrated
resveratrol lifespan extension
in healthy rodents,
only in "metabolically
compromised mammals,"
but isn't that
a pretty accurate description
of most of the U.S. population
these days?
Studies on monkeys fed diets
high in butterfat and sugar
found that resveratrol
decreased
artery and abdominal fat
inflammation.
Combined with the shift
towards normalizing
the lifespans of mice
on high-fat diets,
pharmacology journal
commentaries
were published with titles
like "Resveratrol—pills
to replace a healthy diet?"
speculating whether
"resveratrol is the compound
that will allow us to be
more and more inactive
while eating too much
in general
and too much fat and sugar
in particular."
Yes, a nutrition journal
editorial entitled
"Dodging physical activity
and a healthy diet" conceded,
exercise and dietary
modification
are the "most potent, cheapest,
and easiest ways
to prevent lifestyle-related
chronic diseases,"
but might resveratrol
on its own
"take the edge
off the consequences
of your lifestyle?"
No wonder annual sales
of resveratrol supplements
reached $30 million
in the U.S. alone.
Approaching the peak
in interest
around the time Oprah Winfrey
mentioned it in 2009,
it was estimated
that two-thirds of people
in the United States taking
multiple daily
dietary supplement regimens
included resveratrol.
But what does
the human data show?
I'll cover that, next.
To see if the amount
of resveratrol you get
from drinking red wine
might be beneficial,
researchers looked to
the Chianti region of Tuscany
to determine whether the levels
achieved through diet
help protect
against long-term frailty,
inflammation,
cardiovascular disease,
cancer, or death.
And the answer?
None of the above.
The amount of resveratrol
flowing through their systems
didn't correlate with any
of the health outcomes studied
over nine years of follow-up.
This is surprising
even if only because of
the confounding factors
associated
with wine consumption.
Wine drinkers may be
less likely to smoke
and tend to have higher IQ,
higher parental
education levels,
and higher
socioeconomic status,
which would be expected
to correlate
with better health outcomes.
In contrast, beer drinkers
suffer the opposite—
lower IQ, parental education,
and social class.
The average IQ
of wine-drinking men is 113,
compared to 95
among beer-drinking men.
Yet still, there appeared
to be no correlation
between resveratrol exposure
and well-being.
This may be because
wine-drinking populations
may only be averaging
less than a milligram
of resveratrol a day.
Some "experts" recommend
a daily dose
of 1 gram of resveratrol,
based on the dosing used
in laboratory animal studies.
How much red wine
would you have to drink
to get that much?
Eight thousand glasses a day.
Not a fan of red wine?
A couple thousand gallons
of white wine a day
would do it,
or 5,000 pounds of apples
or grapes,
50,000 pounds of peanuts,
a couple thousand pounds
of chocolate,
or nearly a million bottles
of beer on the wall.
The natural levels
of resveratrol
found in foods and beverages
is not considered
to be sufficient
to elicit health effects,
but that doesn't
necessarily mean
supplements wouldn't work.
However, the bioavailability
of even high-dose resveratrol
has been called into question.
Maximum blood levels after
resveratrol supplementation
can be as low as 40 nanomolar,
which is more than
a hundred times lower
than the 5,000 to 250,000
nanomoles used in vitro
to demonstrate
resveratrol effects.
Even a five-gram dose
of resveratrol
may fall short
of the required level.
This is in contrast to rodents,
in which blood levels
of 32,000 have been reported.
Resveratrol is rapidly absorbed
in humans
but is rapidly metabolized
in our intestine and liver;
so, very little
free resveratrol remains.
But there are about 20
resveratrol-derived metabolites
that can end up in circulation
at much higher levels,
like 20,000 nanomolar,
that might have biological
activity of their own.
What about using
the turmeric trick
of adding black pepper
to suppress
our body's natural
detoxification mechanisms?
It works in mice.
The black pepper compound
piperine
increases maximum
blood concentrations
of resveratrol
more than 1,000 percent,
but, unfortunately, it failed
to significantly alter
blood levels in people.
In a 2014 medical journal
editorial entitled
"The resveratrol fiasco,"
the Editor-in-Chief summarized
the state of the science:
"The conclusions
are quite clear-cut:
after more than 20 years
of well-funded research,
resveratrol has no proven
human activity."
However,
since that publication,
more than 150
human clinical trials
have been published.
What's the update?
Resveratrol was initially
envisaged as an antioxidant,
but meta-analyses
of randomized controlled trials
of resveratrol supplements
failed to find
clinically or even statistically
significant effects
on systemic markers
of oxidative stress,
helping to explain the lack
of apparent DNA protection.
Maybe it only helps with
the metabolically compromised?
As one resveratrol review asked,
"What conclusions would we draw
about the efficacy
of penicillin
if it had been tested
only among persons
in the pink of condition?"
Resveratrol does not appear
to improve
the metabolic function
of nonobese,
nondiabetic individuals,
or even benefit
overweight nondiabetics,
nor does it help people
lose weight,
but resveratrol may help
with blood sugar control
in diabetics.
For almost all outcomes
measured in randomized
controlled trials
of type 2 diabetes,
metabolic syndrome,
or nonalcoholic
fatty liver disease,
the effects of resveratrol
were trivial,
but a meta-analysis did find
that in doses ranging
from 5 to 500 milligrams
twice a day resulted
in an average 20-point drop
in fasting blood sugars.
There was also
a significant benefit
for longer-term
blood sugar control,
though this only appeared
to be the case
in shorter-term studies.
What is the point
of better longer-term control,
if it only works in studies
lasting less than three months.
Diabetic foot ulcers
are the leading cause
of lower-limb amputations
in diabetics.
A randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
of 50 milligrams of resveratrol
twice a day
showed accelerated healing
of diabetic foot ulcers
by about 1 centimeter
over placebo within 60 days.
So, at least there's
one condition it may help.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age” has
been out for about half a year now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.